Guide to the Whaling Logs Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Whaling logs collection
1830-1970
1830-1912
MS 540
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5
(2 boxes, 1 folio)
A collection of eleven logs of whalers mostly sailing from New London and Norwich, Connecticut. Also two from Massachusetts (New Bedford and Provincetown) and one from Sag Harbor, Long Island. Also in the collection are newspaper clippings relating to whaling vessels.
Conditions Governing Access
The entire collection is available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 21 instead of the originals.
Existence and Location of Copies
Log records of thirty-nine whaling and sealing voyages are available on microfilm (3 reels, 35mm.) from Scholarly Resources, Inc., Wilmington, Delaware.
Scope and Contents
A collection of eleven logs of whalers mostly sailing from New London and Norwich, Connecticut. Also two from Massachusetts (New Bedford and Provincetown) and one from Sag Harbor, Long Island. Also in the collection are newspaper clippings relating to whaling vessels.
Shipping -- Connecticut; Shipping -- Massachusetts; Shipping -- New York (State); Whaling ships; Whaling; New Bedford (Mass.); New London (Conn.); Norwich (Conn.); Provincetown (Mass.); Sag Harbor (N.Y.); West Indies; Logs (records); Commodore Perry (Ship); Connecticut (Ship); Hamilton (Ship); Roswell King (Ship); Stonington (Ship)
- Inventory, 1830-1912, 1955, 1970; 2 linear feet (2 boxes, 1 folio)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Entire collection is available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 21 instead of originals.
  Scope and Contents
  For a full description of the logbooks and voyages of these vessels see the print finding aid in Manuscripts and Archives.
  - Logs
    - Bertha (bark) of New Bedford, Mass., 1911 October 21-1912 September 7 (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1)
      Home Port: New Bedford, Massachusetts
      Period of cruise: October, 1911 - September, 1912
      Master: Arthur O. Gibbons
      Type: Bark
      Cargo: Whale oil
      Pages: 128
      The cruise departed from New Bedford and proceeded to the "Western Grounds" in the area of the Azores. Almost from the start they were plagued with lack of equipment or faulty equipment. Ten days out they found they had no matches. A week later they discovered they had no smoke stacks for the try works and had to improvise some till they reached St. Antoine. Then they found faulty blocks and windlass. After that they found one of the try pots cracked, which meant a trip to Barbados for a replacement. The bark never made it, because it couldn't beat to windward. For 103 days they didn't sight a whale. But after ten months they did process some 597 barrels of whale oil, mostly in the central Atlantic. There are many days without log entries, and whaling stamps, where they exist, are sketched in with pencil. The same type of lengthy navigation figures which appear in the log of the "Ellen A. Swift" (Master Gibbons) appear in the same handwriting in this log. Five pages are of special interest. (1) The fly leaf records the navigation locations of four important whaling ports in the Azores. (2) Page 1 records the locations of where whales were sighted during the preceding year. (3) Pg. 134-135 gives oil inventory. (4) Page 140 records a value scale for bbls. of oil. (5) Page 142 records the professional service record of Captain Gibbons from 1877 to 1912 with names of vessels on which he served and his title or rank on each such vessel.
    - Commodore Perry (ship) of New London, Conn., 1834 August 2- 1836 February 29 (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1)
      Home Port: New London, Conn.
      Period of cruise: August, 1834 - January, 1836
      Master: George Hobron
      Type: Ship
      Cargo: Whale oil and bone
      Pages: 120
      This was a whaling cruise to the then popular whaling grounds in the central South Atlantic Ocean between the islands of St. Helena and Tristan da Cunha. Enroute to the South Atlantic they stopped at Fayal in the Azores and counted 21 ships and 4 brigs in port on August 4, 1834. By July 4, 1835 they had taken 16 whales, possibly representing 1000 bbls. of oil. Some of this oil and some whale bone they sent home on the vessel "Palladium". The second year of the cruise they established a base for their operations near Walvis Bay, coast of West Africa, where they stayed for about a month. Unusual action is mention of trying to take more humpback whales - instead of just right whales, sperm whales, and sulphur bottom whales. Great number of whalers sighted and hailed testifies to great whaling activity in this region at the time. All kinds of supplies abounded on the African coast. On the homeward trip very careful navigational computations were entered to aid in plotting the speediest return possible. No whaling stamps appear in this log. Mention is made of contact with Hottentots in procuring supplies.
    - Ellen A. Swift (schooner) of Provincetown, Mass., 1902 December 11- 1904 September 13 (Box 1, Folder 3, Reel 1)
      Home Port: Provincetown, Massachusetts
      Period of cruise: December, 1902 - September, 1904
      Type: Schooner
      Cargo: Whale Oil
      Pages: 199 [Pp. 1-197, 279, 280J (blank pages 216-271, 286, 287)
      This was a whaling voyage to the so-called "Western Banks" in the central Atlantic Ocean between the Azores and Cape Verde Islands. The log is not well kept and lacks daily entries. It is apparent several men had a hand in making the entries. Occasionally a pencil sketch of a whale substitutes for a stamp record. The cruise got off late, being delayed four days by a snowstorm; then they developed leaks, broke the main boom, and found all their potatoes frozen. In the spring of 1903 the Master borrowed a chronometer from the bark "Canton" to be returned or paid for at Fayal. They signed on most of their whaling crew at St. Vincent, (15 men).
      [Of incidental interest: Other random notations (after p. 199) in this volume make mention of three other vessels: - Bark "Alice Knowles"; bark "Andrew H. Lake"; bark "Charles W. Morgan"; which is now at Mystic, Connecticut, museum]
    - Era (schooner) of New London, Conn., 1888 June 13-August 2 (Box 1, Folder 4, Reel 1)
      Period: June - August, 1888
      Master: John O. Spicer
      Cargo: Whale oil and other oil and skins
      Pages: 6 [thress sheets (handwritten on both sides)]
      Routine entries while schooner on location in Davis Strait or Greenland area where stationed for whaling, sealing or hunting operations for indefinite period.
    - Margaret (schooner) of Norwich, Conn., 1909 October 14-1910 July 30 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 2)
      Home Port: Norwich, Connecticut
      Period of cruise: October, 1909 - July, 1910
      Departing from New London on a whaling voyage to the South Atlantic, vessel was found to have a bad leak which could not be repaired at sea. The schooner hastened to Barbados to be dry docked; then waited 29 days for permission from home to repair leak; then lost another week waiting for a dry dock to be free. Lost another ten days repairing leak. Then cruised north of Santo Domingo to Great Inagua Island. No whales, so headed for Norfolk, Va. Lost about 5 days there when 10 of crew quit and new men recruited. Then for two months off Cape Hatteras near the Gulf Stream they had fair ,success whaling. Away from home for 288 days.
    - Talma (schooner) of New London, Conn., 1832 October 21-1833 March 30 (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 3)
      Home Port: New London, Connecticut
      Period of cruise: October, 1832 - March, 1833
      Master: Gordon L. Ailyn
      Cargo: Seal Skins
      Pages: 24
      The beginning pages and the end pages of this log seem to be missing. The log entries commence with the "Talman situated in the South Atlantic, southeast of Argentina, bound for Staten Island and the coast of Tierra del Fuego. Careful navigational notations are recorded as well as frequent soundings, since they followed a coastal route. Constant heavy gales and high seas. They worked the southern coast of Patagonia without result. Fighting snow, sleet and hail they went ashore on Staten Island on November 8, 1832 and took some seals. While working the coast of Tierra del Fulgo, they met other sealers and native Indians; they lost a crewman who fell 50 feet from masthead and was drowned. Log entries end in this area. Many skins taken.
    - Era (schooner) of New London, Conn., 1879 June 24-1880 November 24 (Box 2, Folder 9, Reel 1)
      Period of cruise: June, 1879 - November, 1880
      Master: Captain Spicer, John O.
      Cargo: Whale oil and bone; seal and bear skins
      Pages: 184
      This is a whaling cruise to the Hudson Bay area. Upon arrival there, they set up a base ashore near the entrance to Hudson Strait. They operated from the schooner, but also retained natives to hunt whales in small boats and beach them to be cut up. By the end of August, 1879, pack ice made them give up working Hudson Bay, Fox Channel and Hudson Strait. Mention made that schooner "Delia Hotchkiss" also in the area. By December 1, 1879 pack ice hampering operations. At the end of December with temperature at -28°, they "banked ship" for the winter at edge of pack ice. With native help they engaged in seal and bear hunting during winter - suffering great hardship. By February 1 schooner was 7 miles from edge of ice pack. By February 12, thermometer had been below zero for 6 weeks. By April 15 small boats could be drawn to edge of ice pack, but the "Era" was ice-bound for 8 months and 8 days. During the winter their supply base ashore was robbed of blubber and bone stored there by crew of a vessel identified by natives as the "Aby Bradford." October 25, 1880 they returned to New London. A most arduous cruise.
    - Hamilton (ship) of Sag Harbor, Long Island, New York (with map), 1840 July 3-1842 April 30 (Box 2, Folder 10, Reel 1)
      Home Port: Sag Harbor, Long Island, New York
      Period of cruise: July, 1840 - April, 1842
      Master: Isaac Ludlow
      Pages: 192
      This is an unusually complete account of a successful whaling cruise in three areas off the west coast of Australia. Voyage statistics and whaling stamps are carefully recorded. A printed map of route going and returning, with location of all catches. Captain Ludlow was an active Master. Mention is made of meeting ship with scurvy sufferers to which was transferred potatoes, flour and bread in exchange for a cask of oil (July 15, 1840). The crew got little relief from duty. Christmas, 1841, was at Geographe Bay, S. W. Coast of Australia. Enroute home they spent about a week at St. Helena Island. They took 46 whales on the voyage, producing cargo of 2249 barrels.
    - Roswell King (ship) of New London, Conn., 1886 August 19-1889 June 12 (Box 2, Folder 11, Reel 3)
      Period of cruise: August, 1886 - June, 188?
      Master: David Shepard
      Cargo: Whale (or other oil from seal and walrus) and skins
      Pages: 73
      This is a log of a whaling vessel already on location, probably in the Hudson Strait area, at a place called "King Harbor". The ship was used as an operating base for whaling and hunting seal, walrus, bear and deer. Because of ice, active whaling was only done for about three months. Natives were employed as hunters. The log entries are mostly day-to-day weather reports. It was customary to send out natives starting about March on week-long whaling trips in small boats. On November 5, 188? the ship froze in permaturely (about a month early) and had to be chopped out. In the spring, ship was usually ice-free by end of June. On September 2, 188?, the mate died. Though whales seemed numerous, the ice floes cut down the number captured.
    - Connecticut (ship) of New London, Conn., 1832 September 27-1834 March 12 (Box 3, Reel 1)
      First voyage
      Home Port: New London
      Period of cruise: September, 1832 - March, 1833
      Master: Robert N. Tate
      Pages: 40
      The account of the cruise starts with the ship already in the South Atlantic in the area of Tristan da Cunha, its most successful fishing area. Farther south they found no whales. Returning home they stopped at St. Helena, where the crew got drunk. On the whaling grounds there were 12 ships in sight at one time on November 7, 1832. On December 28, 1832 they reported picking up adrift 17 bb1s. of flour, 12 kegs of lard, and 8 boxes of Havana cigars, and the rudder of a yawl. Final entry of this voyage was made as ship was off Cape Hatteras homeward bound. Whaling stamps are used.
      [First 40 pages of a series of log sheets enclosed in a burlap cover containing also the log of a later cruise of ship CONNECTICUT.]
      Second Voyage
      Period of Cruise: May, l833 - March, 1834
      Cargo: Whale oil and freight from St. Helena
      Pages: 67
      Entries for this voyage start some 400 miles east of New London en route to the South Atlantic Whaling Grounds off Tristan da Cunha via Fayal in the Azores and the Cape Verde Islands. Large number of dead whales she found and processed; large number of whales sank. She liked company while cruising and would keep another whaler she knew in sight for days. Homeward bound she picked up a cargo of seal skins and 138 bundles of whale bone as freight for New London from the Island of St. Helena. Log entries end while homeward bound south of the Cape Verde Islands.
      [Second part (pages 41-102) of a series of log sheets enclosed in a burlap cover containing also log of an earlier cruise of ship CONNECTICUT.]
    - Stonington (ship) of New London, Conn., 1830 July 7-1831 June 20 (Box 3, Reel 3)
      Period of cruise: July, 1830 - June, 1831
      Master: Phi1etus Pierson
      Type: Shp
      Cargo: Whale oil and whale bone
      Pages: 102
      The volume commences with 14 pages of miscellaneous business notations and chronometer readings. The voyage was from New London, Conn., to Patagonia via the Azores. This whaler seemed to be partial to the taking of right whales, since they took no action against the many finbacks sighted. Great number of whales chased but not captured. Abundant whales in the Sputh Atlantic. The ship suffered much from storm damage in the South Atlantic and reported that another whaler the "Acasta" had her try works washed away by a heavy sea sweeping aboard. On October 21, 1830 the log reports that they shot an albatross with a vial tied to its neck containing a message from the whaler "Electra" giving the location of where whales were sighted. Has no whaling stamps.
  - Newspaper clippings re whaling vessels, 1955, 1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 7-8)